<Document>
# Должности

SS14 has a large number of jobs, divided into seven major departments:

## Сервисный отдел
В этот отдел входят глава персонала (ГП), пассажиры, уборщик, клоун, мим, музыкант, шеф-повар, бармен, и другие должности, которые занимаются обслуживанием станции.

It primarily functions as folks who entertain, clean, and serve the rest of the crew, with the exception of passengers who have no particular job beyond getting lost in maintenance.

## Отдел снабжения
В отдел снабжения входят грузчики, утилизаторы, и их глава — квартирмейстер (КМ). Этот отдел занимается распределением грузов и ресурсов по станции, и торговлей на галактическом рынке.

For the most part, this means they scrounge around the station and assorted wrecks to find materials to sell and redistribute, and purchase materials other departments request.

## Medical
[color=#5b97bc]Medical[/color] consists of the medical interns, chemists, medical doctors, and the chief medical officer. As a department it is responsible for taking care of the crew, treat and/or clone the wounded and dead, treat disease, and prevent everyone from dying a horrible, bloody death in a closet somewhere.

Medical is one of the more well-equipped departments, with the ability to locate injured crew using the crew monitor, a nigh infinite supply of chems should chemistry be on-par, and the ability to rapidly diagnose and vaccinate contagious diseases.

## Научный отдел
В научный отдел входят научные ассистенты, учёные и научный руководитель (НР). Этот отдел отвечает за изучение технологий и артефактов, улучшение машин, а также производство полезных для станции устройств.

Scientists should seek out new artifacts to study, as well as solicit departments to help upgrade their machines.

## Инженерный отдел
В инженерный отдел входят технические ассистенты, инженеры, атмосферные техники, и старший инженер (СИ). Этот отдел отвечает за отвечает за обеспечение станции электроэнергией, целостность её корпуса и работоспособность системы подачи воздуха.

Engineering is readily equipped to go safely into space, and as such they should always attempt to repair uninhabitable parts of the station.

## Security
[color=#cb0000]Security[/color] consists of the security cadets, lawyers, detective, security officers, warden, and the head of security. As a department it is responsible for dealing with troublemakers and non-humanoid threats like giant rats and carp.

As a result of this, and the need to walk a fine line, security sometimes is overwhelmed by angry crew (don't kill the clown), and it is important for its members to try and stay on their best behavior.

## Command
[color=#1b67a5]Command[/color] consists of every department head. It is responsible for keeping the station and its departments running efficiently.

Command members should always be relatively competent in their respective departments and attempt to delegate responsibility and direct work.

</Document>
