<Document>
# Шаттлостроение

Строительство шаттла — занятие простое и легкое, хотя и довольно хлопотное по ресурсам и времени. Оно отлично подойдёт тем, у кого много свободного времени и кому хочется вызова.

## С чего начать
<Box>Без чего никак:</Box>
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Thruster"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Gyroscope"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="ComputerShuttle"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="SubstationBasic"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="PortableGeneratorPacman" Caption="P.A.C.M.A.N." />
</Box>
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CableHVStack"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CableMVStack"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CableApcStack"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="APCBasic"/>
</Box>

<Box>Опционально:</Box>
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="AirCanister"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="LightTube"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="AirlockGlassShuttle"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="SMESBasic"/>
</Box>
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="MobCorgiIan"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="NuclearBomb"/>
</Box>

Возьмите стальные листы, металлические стержни, и выдвигайтесь в космос. Как только вы окажетесь в трех или более тайлах от станции, возьмите стержни в руку и кликните на пространство под собой или рядом. Это разместит в пространстве решетку, которую затем с помощью стальных листов можно будет превратить в пол. Расширяйте решётку, кликая стержнями в руке рядом с краем уже имеющейся решётки.

Как только вы разместите решётки в нужной форме, притащите ракетные двигатели и установите их по краям. Для работы они должны быть направлены в космос, а плитка перед ними не должна быть занята. Установите гироскоп где посчитаете нужным, и используйте генератор и подстанцию для организации электропитания. Проведите СВ провод от подстанции, постройте над ним стену, и разместите на ней ЛКП, который будет снабжать питанием приборы на шаттле.

Наконец, установите консоль управления шатлом, и убедитесь что все двигатели и гироскопы получают питание. Если всё так — наши поздравления! У вас получился работоспособный шаттл. Сделать его пригодным для жизни и красивым предлагается читателю самому в качестве упражнения.

  Head out into space with steel sheets and metal rods in hand and click on the edge of the station to place lattice.

  Place a line of lattice about 3-4 tiles away from the station, then start building a platform with lattice.

  Keep doing this until you have a platform that is at least 3x3 in size, which is connected to the station via a single lattice line.

  Once you're finished constructing the base of your shuttle, you can use wirecutters to snip the connecting lattice that joins your new ship and the station.

  This platform is considered a different grid from the station and thus will not have any gravity or be held in place by a station anchor — it can move around freely.

  You can expand your lattice platform further by clicking just off the edge with some rods in hand.

  ## Docking Ports
  Shuttle airlocks serve as docking ports, where ships can dock to stations safely.

  The orientation of docking ports is important, as it determines on which face the shuttle will dock.

  The little numb on the bottom of the docking port determines the direction of the docking port.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="AirlockShuttle"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="AirlockGlassShuttle"/>
  </Box>

  ## Directional Control
  From there, once you have the shape you want, bring out and install thrusters at the edges.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Thruster" Caption="" Rotation="0"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Thruster" Caption="" Rotation="90"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Thruster" Caption="" Rotation="180"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Thruster" Caption="" Rotation="270"/>
  </Box>

  It's a good idea to install four thrusters, one on each side of the platform, to ensure you can move in any direction.

  They must be pointing outward into space to function and will not fire if there's a tile in the way of the nozzle.
  You can rotate thrusters—even anchored ones—using either [color=yellow][bold][keybind="RotateObjectClockwise"][/bold][/color] or [color=yellow][bold][keybind="RotateObjectCounterclockwise"][/bold][/color] to rotate clockwise or counterclockwise.

  Thrusters can be disabled or enabled using [color=yellow][bold][keybind="Use"][/bold][/color] with an empty hand or [color=yellow][bold][keybind="ActivateItemInWorld"][/bold][/color].

  ## Rotational Control
  Now that you have directional control, you'll need to install a gyroscope to control your rotation.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Gyroscope"/>
  </Box>
  The placement of the gyroscope is not as important as the thrusters, but it should be somewhere convenient for you to access and power.

  Note for large mass objects, you may need more than one gyroscope to rotate effectively.

  ## Power
  Now that you have all the systems in place, you'll need to power them.

  For small shuttles, a J.R.P.A.C.M.A.N.-type portable generator is a good choice. It provides straight LV power, so you don't have to worry about transformers.
  Fuel for the generator is also commonly found in maintenance tunnels.

  <Box HorizontalAlignment="Stretch">
    <Box>
      <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="PortableGeneratorJrPacman" Caption="J.R.P.A.C.M.A.N."/>
    </Box>
    <Box>
      <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="WeldingFuelTankFull"/>
    </Box>
  </Box>

  Some stations, however, provide much better generators and compact solutions like the Shuttle APU or the static generator.
  These output HV and will have to be stepped down to MV and LV.
  Luckily, these stations also usually provide wallmount substation boards for this purpose.

  <Box HorizontalAlignment="Stretch">
    <Box>
      <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="GeneratorWallmountAPU"/>
    </Box>
    <Box>
      <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="GeneratorBasic15kW"/>
    </Box>
    <Box>
      <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="SubstationWallBasic"/>
    </Box>
  </Box>

  ## Piloting
  Finally, install the shuttle computer wherever it is convenient and ensure all your thrusters and gyroscopes are receiving power (remember to wire the MV and LV networks!).
  If they are, congratulations! You should have a functional shuttle!

  Making it livable and good-looking is left as an exercise to the reader.
</Document>
