<Document>
  # Xenobiology
  Xenobiology is the breeding and harvesting of slimes and their extracts for scientific purposes. This all takes place in the xenobiology lab where you spawn, and is arguably more dangerous than making bombs if you don't know what you are doing. Which is a good reason to read this!

  ## Home on the Range
  As a Xenobiologist, you’re not going to get out that much until some late game slimes. And until you get those, you won't be bothered much either, *at least in theory*.
  Before you start breeding the slimes, you may want a fire extinguisher in your backpack. You'll most often meet a ravenous, hungry slime while ranching, and having an extinguisher could very well be the difference between a dead slime and a dead you.
  So as you'll be near a lot of slimes, usually before you cull their numbers, and while they're normally docile towards you whom are effectively their God, they occasionally grow resentful for their species' exploitation and try to kill you for no particular reason. In that case, kill the blasphemers with a clear conscience.

  ## Breeding slimes
  ### Feeding
  Slimes eat basically anything, but living mobs are more preferable. One monkey provides enough nutrients for a slime to grow into an adult and then to split. Occasionally there is enough left over that one of the new babies will also grow into an adult.
  - Do NOT enter the pen and bash the monkey, the only thing that will happen is slime will get less food.
  Once they're fed enough, after a while the adult slime will split in 1-4 baby slimes.

  ### Culling
  Time to kill your darlings.
  Decide which baby slimes you don't want to keep and proceed to apply heavy doses of "fire extinguisher" to their face.
  The sheer amount of shower will almost immediately kill a slime. When they stop moving, they're dead and you can pick them up for the next step.

  ### Grinding
  Collect the dead slimes and drag them on top of the slime grinder. It will automatically start and drop a slime core after some time.
  These cores can be injected with any reagent using a syringe, but will violently react only with specific ones. This is usually plasma, water and blood, but you can check them using your slime scanner.

  ## Experimentation
  There is no specific official cheat sheet of what all the slime extracts can possibly do, so it's your lucky chance to catch them all. It's science!

  ## So, you're a Traitor
  What you can get here that can't be gotten easier elsewhere is an EMP and random hostile animals which include a few very deadly ones (CARPS SPACE BEARS ALIUMS SPIDERS HIVEBOTS PINE TREES OH GOD IT'S HORRIFYING).
  Releasing the slimes is somewhat viable, but you will likely get caught doing so, and baby slimes are rather tame (Unless you have red slime essence. Then it's a party.)

  On the plus side, you do have a disposal chute that goes directly to space. Pretty handy for disposing of evidence, or you can make some interesting grenades. Advanced mutation toxin with water in one beaker, fluorosurfactant in the other. Set a timer in the Medbay, drop it and listen to all the people turning into Slimes.
  This is when you laugh to yourself and realize it backfires when all the slimes attack you.
</Document>
